## **NISHAT ANJUM**

□+8801723124778 | Image: Inishat.anjum1789@gmail.com | Image: Im

### About Me\_

I am a committed Software Engineer with a decade of substantial experience in developing and enhancing enterprise-level software solutions. Presently, I hold the position of Principal Software Engineer at an esteemed IT organization in my home country. My proficiency centers around JAVA, JVM-based technologies, Big Data, Software Design Patterns, and Development Methodologies. After a thorough assessment of my extensive professional background and unwavering career aspirations, I am fully dedicated to pursuing a research-focused Master's Program in Computer Science and its various sub-disciplines. I firmly believe that this academic pursuit will pave the way for me to establish a rewarding career as a Computer and Software Specialist in the future.

Education

University of Dhaka Dhaka, Bangladesh

**BSc.** (Honours) in Computer Science and Engineering

2007 - 2011

- CGPA: 3.37/4.00 (German System: 1.9)
- Merit Position: 14th out of 45 students
- Total Credit: 148
- Courses: Software Engineering, Data Structures and Algorithms, Computer Programming Language, Database Management System, Operating System, Computer Networks, Discrete Mathematics, Theory of Computation, Artificial Intelligence
- IELTS: Overall Band Score 7.5 [L-9, R-7.5, W-7, S-6.5]

### Research Interests

- Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning
- Application of Machine Learning in Software Engineering
- Database and knowledge-base systems
- · Data Science and Data Analytics
- Software Engineering

## Academic Research 2

## Title: Throughput Maximization in *Device to Device(D2D)* Enabled Cellular Network

University Of Dhaka

Supervisor: Professor DR. MD. ABDUR RAZZAQUE

In this work, We addressed the spectrum-sharing problem between *cellular and underlying D2D link*. Our main goal was to maximize the throughput of the underlying 3G cellular network in non-orthogonal Resource-Sharing mode. We proposed a *Scheduled resource-sharing Algorithm* for *eNodeB* that intelligently identified potential D2D connection pairs and optimally shared *UpLink* and *DownLink* resources by calculating *SINR* for each pair.

# Technical Expertise\_

**Language:** Java, Python, C/C++, JavaScript, TypeScript, R

Frameworks: Spring-[Boot, Security, MVC, Webflow, Data JPA, Batch, HATEOAS, GraphQL], Python Flask, Angular, Hibernate, JPA, Mockito

Web Services: REST, SOAP

**Middlewares:** WebLogic, WildFly, Tomcat, TomcatEE, Glassfish

Databases: MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, In-memory Data Structure Store-REDIS, Cloud Object Storage - MINIO

Tools: Maven, Gradle, Ant, Postman, Git, Bitbucket, Docker

**OS Platforms:** Linux, Windows, Mac

Big Data: Kafka, Apache KUDU, Apache Spark, Apache Druid, Elasticsearch

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_

#### Tiger IT Bangladesh Limited.

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct 2022 - present

**Principal Software Engineer** 

- Supervising and training a Development team of four software engineers.
- Providing technical guidance to the team and overseeing the technical aspects of four Government projects and upcoming Projects.
- Improving the performance of existing software solutions.
- Investigating Project-related objections and taking necessary measurements to ensure optimal software performance.
- Regularly attend team meetings to discuss projects, brainstorm ideas, and propose solutions to any issues.

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

Oct 2019 - Sept 2022

- Supervised a team of four software engineers to ascertain the successful completion of deliverables.
- Performed various RnD and provided expert support and guidance on architectural changes in ongoing initiatives taken by the company.
- · Continuously contributed to troubleshooting issues in production deployment and performance tuning.
- Reviewed code for defects and quality against technical documents and standard practices.
- · Designing, coding, and debugging new projects

Software Engineer Dec 2015 - Sept 2019

- Extensively re-engineered legacy software system to improve scalability and increased performance by approximately 35%.
- Core architect of a large-scale data migration project involving a highly complex process that successfully migrated approximately 120M Demographic and Biometric data within 42 hours.
- Developed High volume and low latency Restful APIs for various client applications serving **responses less than 30ms.**
- Developed a data streaming pipeline using Apache Kafka that combine messaging and storage of both historical and real-time data.
- Developed a high-performance real-time fast data Analytics application using Apache Druid, KUDU, and Kafka.
- Designed and developed Report modules for multiple ongoing projects which involved complex query writing.
- · Assisted the Junior Software Engineers in solving technical problems and mentored them in writing high-quality code.

Therap BD Ltd. 🗹 Dhaka, Bangladesh

#### **Associate Software Engineer**

Oct 2014 - Dec 2015

- Worked with Technical Staff to understand problems with software and correct them.
- Developed new features for the MAR module of The Therap application.
- Wrote a successful migration script incorporating ETL process to store lookup standard diagnosis codes (e.g. ICD-9/10).
- Solved user reported bugs of different modules in the Therap Application.
- · Learning and experimenting the usability of various technologies in The Therap application.

#### **Junior Software Engineer**

Aug 2012 - Sept 2014

- Learning, installing and reviewing various technologies related to software development.
- Investigated users reported bugs in the code-base and resolved them.
- Did code refactoring to increase readability and performance in different modules.

# Industrial Projects 🗷

### Bangladesh NID application System 🗷

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, JSP, Semantic-UI, JQuery]

• An online public portal where citizens of Bangladesh can apply for NID card and voter registration

#### **Rohingya AFIS And AFRS adjudication System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Python Flask, Angular.js, Spring Boot, Quartz Scheduler]

· An application which ceaselessly crosschecks new voter applications with Rohingya AFIS and AFRS database

#### **CMS system for Election Commission Officials**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot, Spring Security, JWT Token, JSP, Bootstrap, Vue.js]

· Web Application for bangladesh election commission officials to oversee voter registration and NID card applications

#### **Bangladesh Citizen data Migration Project**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot-Scheduling, JDBC, Apache Kafka, Redis]

 A data migration project to migrate 120M voter demographic and Biometric data to ElasticSearch, Apache KUDU, Redis, Minio and Oracle database.

#### Nepal HSE-NP Registration System ✓

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, JSP, Semantic-UI, JQuery]

· An online public portal where Nepal Citizens can apply for high security embossed number plates for their Vehicles.

#### **Nepal HSE-NP Application management System**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, Spring Security, Thymeleaf, Bootstrap, JQuery, Oracle database]

• A web application for Nepal DOTM officials to supervise HSE-NP printing requests.

### Nepal vehicle data migration project

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring-Batch, Spring-JDBC, Oracle Database]

• A data migration project to migrate 35M vehicle data to Oracle database.

#### **Bangladesh NTMC National Datahub Project**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Spring Boot, Spring Security, JWT Token, Apache Kafka, Redis, GraphQL]

· An ETL project for Bangladesh NTMC which accumulates Citizen data from multiple sources and make them searchable and accessible

#### **Vehicle Tracking System - Bangladesh NTMC**

TigerIT Bangladesh

Technology Stack: [Alien JAVA SDK, MQTT, Caffeine Cache, Spring Boot, Spring Scheduling]

• The application unceasingly accumulates vehicle movement information by interfacing with Alien RFID Reader

# Therap Application Technology Stack: [Spring MVC\_ISD FIB\_Hibernate\_IDA\_Oracle D

Therap BD Ltd.

Technology Stack: [Spring MVC, JSP, EJB, Hibernate JPA, Oracle Database]

- · Developed new features in Medication Administration Record(MAR) module to record patients medication record
- Developed a migration project to store lookup standard ICD-9/10 diagnosis code into relational Database

# Academic Projects \_\_\_\_\_

#### Buddy Circle-A Social networking web application 🗹

University Of Dhaka

**Internet Programming** 

2011

· An application developed back in 2012 using spring mvc, JSP, html5, JPA, MySQL

## Tic Tac Toe Game using ATmega32 microcontroller

University Of Dhaka

Computer Peripherals and Interfacing

2010

• A multiplayer tic-tac-toe game written in C language for ATmega32 microcontroller

**Dots and Boxes - Online Multiplayer Game** 

Object Oriented Programming-JAVA

• An online multiplayer game developed using JAVA Applet and socket programming

**Avoid collision Game** University Of Dhaka

Programming Language Fundamental- C Language

• A simple single player game developed using C i-Graphics library

**Unix Shell** 

**Operating System** 

• A simple bash like Unix shell which executes Linux commands using exec().

University Of Dhaka

University Of Dhaka

2010

2008

## Competition and Achievements \_\_\_\_\_

| 2015 | <b>Runner-Up</b> , Women Table Tennis Tournament arranged by Therap BD. Ltd. | Dhaka, Bangladesh    |
|------|--|----------------------|
| 2007 | Education Board Scholarship, HSC Board Exam                                  | Rajshahi, Bangladesh |
| 2005 | Education Board Scholarship, SSC Board Exam                                  | Rajshahi, Bangladesh |

### Interests \_\_\_\_\_

**Table Tennis** Table Tennis is my favorite sport of all. I engage in daily table tennis matches with my colleagues. Workout I am passionate about fitness. Some of my favorite activities are western yoga and low-impact aerobics. Cooking I love baking and Cooking. Baking my birthday cake gives me ultimate joy. I try out new recipes every weekend. **Traveling** I am an avid traveler. I explore both domestic and international destinations whenever the chance arises.

Music I enjoy almost all types of music. However, primarily I love Soul, Country, Indi, pop, Psychedelic, OST, and K-Pop.

## Languages.

**English** Professional proficiency Bengali Native proficiency Hindi Bilingual proficiency